My grandfather was a cobbler.
جدي كان إسكافيًّا.
Back in the day, he made custom-made shoes.
في ذاك الزمن، كان يفصّل أحذية.
I never got to meet him.
لم ألتق به قط.
He perished in the Holocaust.
لقي حتفه في المحرقة.
But I did inherit his love for making,
لكني ورثت حبه للصناعة،
except that it doesn't exist that much anymore.
إلا أنها غير موجودة لتلك الدرجة الآن.
You see, while the Industrial Revolution
ففي الواقع، رغم أن الثورة الصناعية
did a great deal to improve humanity,
قدمت الكثير لتحسين الإنسانية،
it eradicated the very skill
إلا إنها قضت على المهارة عينها
that my grandfather loved,
التي أحبها جدي،
and it atrophied craftsmanship as we know it.
وبددت الحرفية كما نعرفها.
But all of that is about to change with 3D printing,
لكن كل ذلك على وشك التغير مع الطباعة ثلاثية،
and it all started with this,
وكلها بدأت بهذا،
the very first part
أول قطعة
that was ever printed.
طبعت أبدا.
It's a little older than TED.
إنها أقدم قليلا من TED.
It was printed in 1983
طبعت في عام 1983
by Chuck Hull,
لـتشَاك هل،
who invented 3D printing.
الذي اخترع الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد.
But the thing that I want to talk to you about today,
لكن ما أريد أن أتحدث لكم عنه اليوم،
the big idea that I want to discuss with you,
الفكرة الكبيرة التي أريد مناقشتها معكم،
is not that 3D printing
ليست أن الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد
is going to catapult us into the future,
ستقذفنا للمستقبل
but rather that it's actually going
بل أنها في الواقع
to connect us with our heritage,
ستربطنا مع تراثنا،
and it's going to usher in a new era
وستستهلّ حقبة جديدة
of localized, distributed manufacturing
من الصناعة المحلية المتوزعة
that is actually based
والمبنية حقيقةً
on digital fabrication.
على الفبركة الرقمية.
So think about useful things.
فكّروا في الأمور المفيدة.
You all know your shoe size.
جميعكم تعرفون مقاس أحذيتكم.
How many of you know the size
كم منكم يعرف مقاس
of the bridge of your nose
جسر أنفه؟
or the distance between your temples?
أو المسافة بين أصداغه؟
Anybody?
هل من أحد؟
Wouldn't it be awesome if you could,
ألن يكون رائعا إن استطعت،
for the first time, get eyewear
للمرة الأولى، الحصول على نظارات
that actually fits you perfectly
تناسبك تماما
and doesn't require any hinge assembly,
ولا تتطلب أي تجميع مفاصل
so chances are, the hinges are not going to break?
دون أن تنكسر المفاصل؟
But the implications of 3D printing
لكن تداعيات الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد
go well beyond the tips of our noses.
تتجاوز أطراف أنوفنا.
When I met Amanda for the first time,
حين قابلت أماندا لأول مرة،
she could already stand up and walk a little bit
كانت قد استطاعت الوقوف والمشي قليلا
even though she was paralyzed from the waist down,
مع أنها كانت مشلولة من الخصر وأسفل،
but she complained to me that her suit
لكنها تذمرت لي أن بدلتها
was uncomfortable.
كانت غير مريحة.
It was a beautiful robotic suit
كانت بدلة روبوتية جميلة
made by Ekso Bionics,
صنعت من "إكسو بايونكس"،
but it wasn't inspired by her body.
لكنها لم تكن مستوحاة من جسدها.
It wasn't made to measure.
لم تكن مصنوعة للمقياس.
So she challenged me to make her something
لذا تحدّتني أن أصنع لها شيئا
that was a little bit more feminine,
أكثر أنوثة،
a little bit more elegant,
أكثر أناقة،
and lightweight,
خفيفا،
and like good tailors,
وكالخياطين البارعين
we thought that we would measure her digitally.
اعتقدنا أننا سنقيسها رقميا.
And we did. We built her an amazing suit.
وفعلنا. بنينا لها بدلة رائعة.
The incredible part about what I learned
الأمر العظيم عما تعلمته
from Amanda is a lot of us are looking at 3D printing
من أماندا هو أن كثيرا منا ينظرون للطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد
and we say to ourselves,
ونقول لأنفسنا
it's going to replace traditional methods.
أنها ستستبدل طرقا تقليدية.
Amanda looked at it and she said,
أماندا نظرت لها وقالت،
it's an opportunity for me
إنها فرصة لي
to reclaim my symmetry
لاستعادة تناظري
and to embrace my authenticity.
واعتناق أصالتي.
And you know what? She's not standing still.
وتعلمون ماذا الآن؟ إنها لم تخمد.
She now wants to walk in high heels.
أصبحت الحين تريد المشي على كعب عال.
It doesn't stop there.
وليس هذا فقط.
3D printing is changing
الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد باتت تغير
personalized medical devices as we know them,
الأجهزة الصحية الشخصية كما نعرفها
from new, beautiful, conformal,
من دعامات للجنف جديدة وجميلة
ventilated scoliosis braces
وامتثالية ومهوّاة،
to millions of dental restorations
للملايين من الترميمات الأسنانية
and to beautiful bracings
ولدعّامات الجميلة
for amputees,
للمبتورين،
another opportunity to emotionally reconnect
فرصة جديدة لإعادة التواصل
with your symmetry.
مع تناسقك.
And as we sit here today,
ونحن نجلس هنا اليوم،
you can go wireless on your braces
تستطيع أن تستغني عن الأسلاك لتقويم أسنانك
with clear aligners,
بمرصّفات شفافة،
or your dental restorations.
أو ترميماتك الأسنانية.
Millions of in-the-ear hearing aids
الملايين من السماعات داخل الأذن
are already 3D printed today.
قد أصبحت تطبع بأبعاد ثلاثة اليوم.
Millions of people are served today
الملايين من الناس يعاونون اليوم
from these devices.
من قبل هذه الأجهزة.
What about full knee replacements,
ماذا عن استبدال كامل للركبة،
from your data, made to measure,
من معطياتك، عملت للقياس،
where all of the tools and guides are 3D printed?
حيث كل الأدوات والأدلة مطبوعة ثلاثية الأبعاد؟
G.E. is using 3D printing
"جي. إي" تستخدم الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد
to make the next generation LEAP engine
لصنع الجيل الجديد لمحرك LEAP
that will save fuel to the tune
والذي سوف يوفّر وقودًا
of about 15 percent
تقريبا بمقدار 15%
and cost for an airline
وتكلفة السفر الجوي
of about 14 million dollars.
بحوالي 14 مليون دولار.
Good for G.E., right?
جيد لـ “جي. إي." صحيح؟
And their customers and the environment.
ولعملائهم وللبيئة.
But, you know, the even better news
ولكن، تعلمون، الأخبار الأفضل
is that this technology is no longer reserved
هي أن هذه التكنولوجيا لم تعد محجوزة
for deep-pocketed corporations.
للشركات الغنية.
Planetary Resources, a startup
"بلانيتاري ريسورسز"، شركة محدثة
for space explorations
للاستكشاف الفضائي
is going to put out its first space probe later this year.
ستضع أول مسابرها لاحقا هذا العام.
It was a fraction of a NASA spaceship,
كانت جزء من سفينة لـناسا،
it costs a fraction of its cost,
تكلّف جزء من ثمنها،
and it's made with less than a dozen moving parts,
وقد صنعت بأقل من درزن من الأجزاء المتحركة،
and it's going to be out in space later this year.
وستوضع في الفضاء لاحقا هذه السنة.
Google is taking on this very audacious project
جوجل تولت مشروعا جريئا
of making the block phone, the Ara.
لصنع جوّال القطع، الـ"آرا".
It's only possible because of the development
إنه ممكن فقط بسبب تطور
of high-speed 3D printing that for the first time
الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد السريعة، والتي للمرة الأولى
will make functional, usable modules
ستصنع وحدات عملية وفعالة
that will go into it.
لتدخل فيه.
A real moonshot, powered by 3D printing.
طلقة حقيقية للقمر، بفضل الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد.
How about food?
ماذا عن الأكل؟
What if we could, for the first time,
ماذا لو استطعنا، للمرة الأولى،
make incredible delectables
عمل ملذات عظيمة
like this beautiful TED Teddy here,
مثل دب TED الدمية الجميل هذا،
that are edible?
والصالح للأكل؟
What if we could completely change the experience,
ماذا لو استطعنا تغيير التجربة بالكامل،
like you see with that absinthe serving
كما ترون مع هذه الحصة من الأفسنتين
that is completely 3D printed?
المطبوعة بالثلاثية الأبعاد كليا؟
And what if we could begin to put ingredients
وماذا لو قدرنا أن نبدأ بوضع مكونات
and colors and flavors in every taste,
وألوان ونكهات لكل ذوق،
which means not only delicious foods
ما يعني ليس فقط أطعمة لذيذة
but the promise of personalized nutrition
بل إمكانية تغذية مخصصة شخصيا
around the corner?
في المتناول؟
And that gets me to one of the biggest deals about 3D printing.
وهذا يحضرني لأحد أهم الأمور عن الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد.
With 3D printing, complexity is free.
مع الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد، التعقيد مجاني.
The printer doesn't care
لا تهتم الطابعة
if it makes the most rudimentary shape
إن كانت تصنع أبسط الأشكال
or the most complex shape,
أم أعقدها،
and that is completely turning design
وهذا يقلب التصميم والتصنيع
and manufacturing on its head as we know it.
كما نعرفه رأسا على عقب.
Many people think that 3D printing will be
يعتقد الكثير أن الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد ستكون
the end of manufacturing as we know it.
نهاية التصنيع كما نعرفه.
I think that it's the opportunity to put
أنا أعتقد أنها الفرصة لوضع
tomorrow's technology in the hands of youngsters
تكنولوجيا الغد في أيدي شباب اليوم
that will create endless abundance
التي سوف تصنع وفرة لا نهائية
of job opportunities,
من فرص العمل،
and with that,
وبهذا،
everybody can become an expert maker
الكل يقدر أن يصير منتجًا محترفًا
and an expert manufacturer.
وصانعًا محترفًا.
That will take new tools.
يتطلب هذا أدوات جديدة.
Not everybody knows how to use CAD,
لا يعرف الكل كيف يستخدم الـ"كاد"،
so we're developing haptics,
لذا فإننا نطوّر ملماسات،
perceptual devices
أجهزة حسية
that will allow you to touch
تسمح لك بلمس
and feel your designs
والشعور بتصاميمك
as if you play with digital clay.
وكأنك تلعب بمعجون رقمي.
When you do things like that,
لما تفعل أشياء هكذا،
and we also developed things that take
وقد طورنا أيضا أشياء تأخذ
physical photographs that are instantly printable,
صورًا مادية قابلة للطبع فورًا،
it will make it easier to create content,
سيجعل ذلك من السهل تكوين المحتوى،
but with all of the unimagined,
ولكن مع كل ما لم يتخيل،
we will also have the unintended,
يأتي ما لا يقصد،
like democratized counterfeiting
مثل ترويج التزوير،
and ubiquitous illegal possession.
وانتشار الامتلاك غير القانوني.
So many people ask me,
لذا فإن الكثير يسألني،
will we have a 3D printer in every home?
هل سنحوز على طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد في كل منزل؟
I think it's the wrong question to ask.
أعتقد أن هذا السؤال الخاطئ.
The right question to ask is,
السؤال الصحيح هو،
how will 3D printing change my life?
كيف ستغير الطباعة الثلاثية الأبعاد حياتي؟
Or, in other words, what room in my house
أو بكلمات أخرى، في أي غرف منزلي
will 3D printing fit in?
سوف يليق وضع الطابعة الثلاثية الأبعاد؟
So everything that you see here
كل ما ترونه هنا
has been 3D printed,
قد طبع بأبعاد ثلاثة،
including these shoes
بما فيه هذه الأحذية
at the Amsterdam fashion show.
من عرض أزياء أمستردام.
Now, these are not my grandfather's shoes.
الآن، هذه ليست أحذية جدي.
These are shoes that represent
هذه الأحذية تمثل
the continuation of his passion
استمرارية شغفه
for hyper-local manufacturing.
للتصنيع المحلي.
My grandfather didn't get to see Nike
لم يسع لجدي أن يرى "نايكي"
printing cleats for the recent Super Bowl,
تطبع الأحذية المسامير لل"سوپر بول" الأخير،
and my father didn't get to see me standing
ولم يسع لأبي أن يراني واقفا
in my hybridized 3D printed shoes.
في حذائي المهجن المطبوع بأبعاد ثلاثة.
He passed away three years ago.
توفي قبل ثلاثة أعوام.
But Chuck Hull, the man that invented it all,
لكن تشاك هل، الرجل الذي اخترعها كلها،
is right here in the house today,
موجود هنا في المجلس،
and thanks to him,
وبفضله
I can say, thanks to his invention, I can say
أستطيع القول، بفضل اختراعه، أستطيع القول
that I am a cobbler too,
بأنني إسكافي أيضا،
and by standing in these shoes
وبوقوفي في هذه الأحذية
I am honoring my past
أنا أكرّم ماضيّ،
while manufacturing the future.
بينما أصنّع المستقبل.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)